ASIF IQBAL RAHAMAN

 □ asif256000+job@gmail.com https://linkedin.com/in/asif-iqbal-r/ https://github.com/asif256000/

 Blacksburg, VA, USA https://asifiqbal.xvz/

As a Computer Science Graduate with 3+ years of industry experience and a year in academic research, I am actively seeking full-time role from June 2024. My experience in diverse domains position me well to contribute to innovative and challenging projects.

SKILLS

Programming: Python, Rust, Javascript, SQL, Bash, Shell Script, HTML, CSS, C++, Java, GoLang, VueJS, ReactJS

Frameworks: Flask, FastAPI, RestAPI, Pandas, Numpy, AWS-CDK, PyTorch, Win32, PyautoGUI, Matplotlib, JSON, OpenCV, Django, Pillow

Tools: Git, Jenkins, Docker, Unix, Linux, Nginx, Supervisor, MySQL, MongoDB, AWS, Selenium, Airflow, Azure, Expo

EDUCATION

VIRGINIA TECH - BLACKSBURG, US

Aug 2022 - May 2024

Master of Engineering in Computer Science

CGPA: 3.9/4.0

Courses: Al Tools for Software Delivery, Natural Language Processing, Data Analysis, Applications of Machine Learning, Computer Vision

VIT UNIVERSITY - VELLORE. IN

Aug 2015 - May 2019

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science

CGPA: 8.0/10.0

Courses: Data Structures & Algorithms, Database Management, Software Development, Data Mining, Cyber Security, Network Architecture

EXPERIENCE

DEPARTMENT OF COMPUTATIONAL CELL BIOLOGY, VIRGINIA TECH - BLACKSBURG, US Software Developer

Oct 2022 - May 2024

- Designed an automated simulation of cell cycle with boolean model of protein interactions with significantly better efficiency and accuracy.
- Utilized Pandas, Numpy for data manipulation, database APIs for data validation and dataclass to structure inputs in Python for the project.
- Achieved a **5x increase** in simulation speed for model perturbation analysis by implementing parallel processing and algorithm optimization on the ARC@VT supercomputer for automated improvement of exponentially growing (approx 1.6M interactions) cell interaction models.
- Resulted in a research publication available at biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.10.30.564745v1 under review of PLOS One journal.

SECLORE TECHNOLOGIES PVT. LTD. - MUMBAI. IN **Product Engineer**

Dec 2021 - Jul 2022

- Significantly reduced customer onboarding from several days to few hours, enhanced operational efficiency by automating DevOps with AWS-CDK and developed a cloud-based deployment solution leveraging AWS CloudFormation, ECS, DynamoDB, and CloudWatch.
- Optimized deployment by designing scalable infrastructure as code with Docker and Jenkins for containerization and pipeline execution.
- Fostered teamwork and agile development, delivering the initial framework in 4 months utilizing CI/CD principles in a team of 3.

ERICSSON INDIA GLOBAL SERVICES PVT. LTD. - BANGALORE, IN Software Engineer

Jan 2019 - Jul 2021

- Developed a rule-based recommendation engine using Pandas and Numpy for network performance analysis, achieving a 36% automation gain for international telecom clients through enhanced data processing and analysis, and optimizing with parallel computing.
- Constructed an automated API system for daily processing of ~30GB data from datalakes, improving data handling efficiency by cleaning. categorizing, and storing data as parguet files using Pandas and requests library, facilitating faster access for the recommendation engine.
- Engineered an RPA framework to streamline network management operations, securing 35% boost in automation efficiency by utilizing OpenCV, Selenium, win32 for targeted actions, NoSQL and MySQL for data integration, with backend developed using Rest API.
- Integrated the RPA framework with Ericsson's BotStore platform using internal APIs, streamlining the automation process.

PROJECTS

Personal Website with FastAPI, AWS and Nginx

Jan 2024

- Embraced hands-on learning approach by designing a dynamic website using FastAPI, SQLAlchemy, Jinja2 in Python, PyTest for testing automation, docker-compose for containerization of the application and deployed in AWS EC2 with Nginx proxy server for efficient routing.
- Designed the website with a forward-thinking structure to potentially support multiple user profiles, enhancing scalability and engagement.

EEG Signal to Text Extraction

Nov 2023

- Replicated the pioneering research of Wang, Ji et al to convert EEG signal to text tokens by fine-tuning BART model with custom data.
- Implemented zero-shot algorithm using PyTorch to classify the generated texts for verifying sentiment analysis of EEG signals.

Multiple Object Tracking using FairMOT and GAN

Dec 2023

- Constructed a novel architecture for multiple object tracking, integrating FairMOT with Generative Adversarial Networks (GAN).
- Demonstrated that isolating the generator in a separate layer in the architecture diminishes the tracking performance, as the discriminator readily distinguishes between fake and real data based on layer origin, highlighting the importance of architecture design.

Football (Soccer) Commentary Generation with Fine-Tuned GPT Model

Ongoing

- Enhancing artificial intelligence generated commentary realism by fine-tuning GPT model with real-game data through prompt engineering.
- Leveraging a text-to-speech and translation API to emulate Peter Drury's voice for multilingual commentary and enhanced accessibility.

CERTIFICATIONS & AWARDS

Python for Data Science and Machine Learning Bootcamp

Udemy Certificate - May 2021

Improving Deep Network: Hyperparameter Tuning, Regularization & Optimization

Coursera Certificate - Jul 2020

Neural Networks and Deep Learning

Coursera Certificate - Jan 2020

Bi-annual Galactic Award from Ericsson (2020) for achieving outstanding business excellence with data automation framework.